<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: nginx | Archaic Positives]]></title>
  <link href="http://ianmiller.nyc/blog/categories/nginx/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ianmiller.nyc/"/>
  <updated>2014-10-30T10:48:20-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://ianmiller.nyc/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ian Miller]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Explanation of NGinx and Passenger]]></title>
    <link href="http://ianmiller.nyc/blog/2013/11/04/explanation-of-nginx-and-passenger/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-04T20:19:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://ianmiller.nyc/blog/2013/11/04/explanation-of-nginx-and-passenger</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>NGinx is a open-source proxy server that primarily serves HTTP and HTTPS protocols.  Nginx was created to achieve three main goals: concurrency (process in which computations are executed simultaneously across several systems), high performance, and low memory usage.  It utilizes an event-driven approach to server requests, and allocates responses based upon server traffic and handling.  It has become a viable alternative to the Apache server model, which uses a process-driven methodology for handling large server requests.<br/>
NGinx has emerged largely as a result of increased demand for online services and the rise of the web as a platform.  Unlike Apache, NGinx has a master process that delegates work to worker processes, and it is designed handle a large number of server connections with a small amount of memory.</p>

<p>A number of companies, according to Wired, have run into scalability issues with Apache, and have transitioned to NGinx.  Facebook, Dropbox, and Wordpress are sites that utilize the NGinx server platform.</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://www.wired.com/wiredenterprise/wp-content/uploads//2012/02/Screen-shot-2012-02-09-at-5.16.17-PM.png">http://www.wired.com/wiredenterprise/wp-content/uploads//2012/02/Screen-shot-2012-02-09-at-5.16.17-PM.png</a>&#8221;></p>

<p>NGinx does not have a module load feature like Apache does, but that is where Passenger steps in, as it automates the module loading process.</p>

<p>Passenger is an Rack application server software that is often used in conjunction with NGinx.  Similarly with mod_php for hosting PHP apps on Apache, Passenger simplifies the process of hosting Ruby apps on NGinx.  Passenger automates the process of starting/stopping a server, restarting after a server crash, and dynamically adjusts the number of processes on a server based on traffic.  It also allows the server to run more than 1 instance of the app, allowing greater use of server resources.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
